NGINX JS DOM — Developer Manual

Introduction

What NGINX JS DOM Is

NGINX is deliberately static: its configuration is read once at startup (or reload) and compiled into kernel-level data structures. This rigidity is a feature — it makes nginx predictable, fast, and easy to reason about — but it creates friction whenever runtime adaptability is required: upstream weights that need to track backend health scores, virtual hosts generated from a tenant database, SSL certificates that rotate on a schedule, or request routing rules that depend on live feature-flag state.

NGINX JS DOM embeds QuickJS [https://bellard.org/quickjs/] (a lightweight ES2020+ [https://tc39.es/ecma262/2020/] JavaScript engine) directly into nginx and exposes the entire nginx configuration as a structured JavaScript object tree called the Configuration Object Model (COM). Through the COM, JavaScript can:

•

Read the full live configuration of every module in every server and location.

•

Write configuration properties — upstream peer weights, SSL certificates, location directives, gzip settings, and much more — with immediate effect, either for the current worker or atomically for all workers at once.

•

Generate server and location blocks at parse time, before nginx has even finished reading its configuration file, and at run-time, when traffic events are processed by nginx workers in their nginx event loops.

•

Handle requests in JavaScript, using the same event-driven async model as nginx itself.

•

Offload CPU-intensive work to background threads (Workers) without blocking the nginx event loop.

•

Maintain shared mutable state across all nginx worker processes using SharedWorkers and SharedArrayBuffers.

The result is an nginx that can be programmed rather than merely configured — without restarting, without patching C code, and without sacrificing the performance or stability of the core server.

Intended Audience

This manual assumes:

•

Familiarity with nginx configuration syntax and core concepts (workers, upstreams, locations, modules). See the NGINX Beginner’s Guide [https://nginx.org/en/docs/beginners_guide.html] and the full module reference [https://nginx.org/en/docs] if you need a refresher.

•

Working knowledge of modern JavaScript (ES2020): async/await, Promises, import/export, SharedArrayBuffer, Atomics. See the ECMAScript 2020 specification [https://tc39.es/ecma262/2020/] or any ES2020 reference.

You do not need to know C or QuickJS internals to use the JS DOM API.

A Map of the Moving Parts

The sections that follow cover these components:

Component │ What it gives you

js_preprocess │ Runs JavaScript during config parsing; the script writes config text back into the parser. Use it to generate server/location blocks from files, environment variables, or external sources.

js_init_http │ Runs JavaScript after the http {} block is parsed but before directives are merged. Can read already-parsed servers and inject new ones.

js_source │ Evaluates JavaScript in the master process after all config has been parsed. This is where you install request handlers, set up Workers and SharedWorkers, and perform any pre-fork initialisation.

Request handlers │ JavaScript async functions assigned to location.handler. Each request runs through the nginx event loop; await suspends the handler without blocking any other request.

COM │ The nginx global object tree. Read live config values; write mutations that take effect immediately.

Workers │ Standard Web Worker API. A per-nginx-worker background thread for CPU-bound work. Does not block the event loop.

SharedWorkers │ A single long-lived thread in the master process, connected to every nginx worker via UNIX sockets. The canonical place for mutable state that must be consistent across all workers.

SharedArrayBuffers + Atomics │ Binary shared-memory regions (MDN reference) accessible from any thread with zero copy. Combined with Atomics, they enable lock-free counters, mutexes, and condition variables.

Accept control │ nginx.suspendAcceptance() / nginx.suspendAllWorkers() — pause connection acceptance during a mutation window, then resume.

Resource limits │ nginx.workerMemoryLimit and nginx.workerRequestTimeout cap heap usage and CPU time per request; JS exceptions are caught; the worker survives.

Architecture

Lifecycle Overview

nginx start
│
├─ Config file parsing begins (ngx_conf_parse)
│ │
│ ├── js_preprocess /gen.js ◄── STAGE 1: runs immediately, mid-parse
│ │ • Ephemeral JS runtime (freed after script returns)
│ │ • config.write(text) injects text back into the parser
│ │ • nginx.http, nginx.stream, etc. do NOT exist yet
│ │
│ ├── ... rest of nginx.conf parsed (servers, locations, upstreams) ...
│ │
│ └── js_init_http /init.js ◄── STAGE 2: runs after http{} block parses
│ • Ephemeral runtime, scoped to this directive
│ • config.write(text) still works; new servers get full merge treatment
│ • nginx.http.servers[] is readable (servers parsed before this line)
│
├─ init_conf (master process) ◄── STAGE 3: js_source scripts evaluated here
│ │
│ ├── JS runtime + context created (persists, will be inherited by workers)
│ ├── All js_source files evaluated in order
│ │ • Install location.handler = fn assignments
│ │ • Create SharedWorkers (they start running immediately)
│ │ • Set nginx.workerMemoryLimit / nginx.workerRequestTimeout
│ │ • Any other pre-fork setup
│ └── SharedWorker threads spawned; channels to each future worker prepared
│
├─ fork() × worker_processes ◄── STAGE 4: worker processes created
│ │
│ └── init_process (per worker)
│ • JS runtime inherited via copy-on-write
│ • No re-evaluation of scripts; all handlers already installed
│ • Worker attaches its UNIX socket channels to each SharedWorker
│
└─ Event loop (per worker) ◄── STAGE 5: runtime
│
└── HTTP/stream request arrives
• location.handler(req) called
• await suspends handler; event loop serves other requests
• COM reads/writes apply to THIS worker's copy (or all, with
suspendAllWorkers)
• req.json() / req.respond() sends the response

Process and Thread Topology

┌─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐
│ Master process │
│ │
│ ┌──────────────────────┐ ┌──────────────────────┐ │
│ │ SharedWorker A │ │ SharedWorker B │ │
│ │ (pthread) │ │ (pthread) │ │
│ │ long-lived JS state │ │ e.g. rate-limiter │ │
│ └──────────────────────┘ └──────────────────────┘ │
└────────────────────────┬────────────────────────────────────────┘
│ AF_UNIX SEQPACKET
│ each worker gets one channel per SharedWorker
┌────────────┼────────────┐
│ │ │
▼ ▼ ▼
┌──────────────┐ ┌──────────────┐ ┌──────────────┐
│ Worker 0 │ │ Worker 1 │ │ Worker N │
│ JS Runtime │ │ JS Runtime │ │ JS Runtime │
│ (CoW copy) │ │ (CoW copy) │ │ (CoW copy) │
│ Event loop │ │ Event loop │ │ Event loop │
│ JS Workers │ │ JS Workers │ │ JS Workers │
└──────────────┘ └──────────────┘ └──────────────┘

Key properties of this topology:

•

Each nginx worker process has its own independent JS runtime. QuickJS is not thread-safe; no runtime is ever shared between processes.

•

Workers inherit the master’s runtime via copy-on-write after fork(). Scripts do not need to be re-evaluated; all handler functions, SharedWorker references, and global variables are ready immediately.

•

SharedWorkers run in the master process as pthreads, outside any worker. Each worker communicates with a SharedWorker over a dedicated UNIX socket channel. This is the only channel through which workers can share mutable JS state.

•

JS Workers (lowercase) are pthreads spawned inside a worker process. They exist to offload work from the event loop and are private to their nginx worker.

COM Ownership and Mutation Scope

All COM mutations go through one of three scopes:

Scope │ Mechanism │ Visible to

Per-request snapshot │ r.location.setWriteMode("local") — writes a per-request copy of the location config │ This request only; reversed when the request pool is freed

This worker only │ Direct COM write (default) │ All subsequent requests on this worker process

All workers atomically │ await nginx.suspendAllWorkers() → mutate → await nginx.resumeAllWorkers() │ All workers, once they resume

Quick Start

This section goes from "hello world" to "live upstream rebalancing" in four steps, each building on the previous one.

Hello World Handler

# nginx.conf
js_source /etc/nginx/js/init.js;
events { }
http {
server {
listen 80;
location /hello { } # placeholder — handler installed from JS
}
}

// /etc/nginx/js/init.js
// This file is evaluated once in the master process after config parsing.
// All location.handler assignments made here are inherited by every worker.
const loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(l => l.path === '/hello');
loc.handler = (req) => {
// req is a NginxRequest object. text() is a convenience shorthand
// for respond(200, {'Content-Type': 'text/plain'}, body).
req.text('Hello from JS DOM!\n');
};

Reading Request Data

// Read everything you might want from an incoming request.
loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Basic identity
const method = req.method; // "GET", "POST", …
const uri = req.uri; // "/hello"
const args = req.args; // raw query string: "a=1&b=2"
const params = req.queryParams; // {a: "1", b: "2"}
const scheme = req.scheme; // "http" or "https"
const host = req.host; // "example.com"
// Network info
const client = req.remoteAddr; // "203.0.113.42"
const port = req.remotePort; // 54321
const server = req.serverAddr; // "192.0.2.1"
// Headers (read-only object; keys are lowercased)
const ua = req.headers['user-agent'];
const ct = req.contentType; // shorthand for content-type header
// Cookies: {name: "value", …}
const session = req.cookies['session_id'];
// nginx variables — readable and writable via req.variables
const xff = req.variables['http_x_forwarded_for'];
req.variables['my_custom_var'] = 'set-from-js';
// Request body (requires await — nginx reads it asynchronously)
const body = await req.readBody(); // returns string
req.json({
method, uri, client, ua, session,
bodyLength: body.length
});
};

Async Fetch and Transform

// Non-blocking upstream call. While this handler awaits, the nginx event
// loop freely serves other requests on this worker.
loc.handler = async (req) => {
// req.fetch() performs an HTTP subrequest through nginx's upstream
// machinery. It returns a Promise that resolves with a Response object.
const res = await req.fetch('http://api.internal/v1/prices');
const data = await res.json();
// Apply transformation
const adjusted = data.items.map(item => ({
...item,
price: (item.price * 1.10).toFixed(2) // add 10% margin
}));
req.json({ items: adjusted });
};

HTTP request arrives at worker
│
▼
loc.handler called synchronously
│
└─ await req.fetch(...)
│
│ [event loop resumes; other requests served here]
│
▼ upstream response received (epoll fires)
Promise resolves
│
▼
res.json() parsed
│
▼
req.json(result) → HTTP response sent

Live Upstream Rebalancing

// An admin endpoint that atomically updates upstream peer weights across
// all workers — no nginx restart, no dropped connections.
const adminLoc = nginx.http.servers
.find(s => s.names.includes('admin.internal'))
.locations.find(l => l.path === '/upstream/rebalance');
adminLoc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = await req.readBody();
const weights = JSON.parse(body); // { "192.0.2.10:8080": 5, "192.0.2.11:8080": 10 }
// Step 1: pause all workers so the change is seen atomically.
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
// Step 2: apply weights.
const peers = nginx.http.upstreams
.find(u => u.name === 'backend').peers;
for (const peer of peers) {
if (weights[peer.addr] !== undefined) {
peer.weight = weights[peer.addr];
}
}
// Step 3: resume — all workers pick up the new weights immediately.
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
req.json({ applied: true, peers: peers.map(p => ({addr: p.addr, weight: p.weight})) });
};

Request Handlers

Installing a Handler

A location handler is a JavaScript function assigned to location.handler during js_source evaluation (init_conf time):

nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/api')
.handler = async (req) => { ... };

The function receives one argument — a NginxRequest object — and may be synchronous or async. A location that has no JS handler falls through to nginx’s normal content processing (proxy, static files, etc.).

NginxRequest Reference

4.2.1. Identity and Network

Property │ Type │ Description

method │ string │ HTTP method: "GET", "POST", "DELETE", …

uri │ string │ Request URI without query string

args │ string │ Raw query string ("a=1&b=foo")

queryParams │ object │ Query string parsed to key→value pairs

scheme │ string │ "http" or "https"

host │ string │ Value of the Host header

remoteAddr │ string │ Client IP address

remotePort │ number │ Client TCP port

serverAddr │ string │ Server-side IP the connection arrived on

serverPort │ number │ Server-side port

httpVersion │ string │ "1.0", "1.1", or "2.0"

keepalive │ boolean │ Whether the connection is keep-alive

isInternal │ boolean │ true for subrequests

startTime │ number │ Request start time (milliseconds, Unix epoch)

requestLength │ number │ Total bytes received (headers + body)

connection │ number │ nginx connection serial number

4.2.2. Headers

Property / Method │ Type │ Description

headers │ object │ Request headers; keys are lowercased

contentType │ string │ Shorthand for headers['content-type']

contentLength │ number │ Parsed Content-Length value

getHeader(name) │ string │ Get a response header already set

setHeader(name, v) │ — │ Set a response header

removeHeader(name) │ — │ Remove a response header

4.2.3. Body

Property / Method │ Type │ Description

body │ string | null │ Request body if already buffered; null otherwise

readBody() │ Promise<string> │ Read the full request body (async)

4.2.4. Cookies and Variables

Property / Method │ Type │ Description

cookies │ object │ Cookie jar: {name: "value", …}

variables │ object │ Exotic r/w proxy over nginx variables

getVar(name) │ string │ Read one nginx variable

setVar(name, val) │ — │ Set one nginx variable

4.2.5. Location and Server Context

Property │ Type │ Description

location │ NginxLocation │ The matched location’s COM object (mutable within this request)

upstream │ object | null │ Upstream peer info if request was proxied

4.2.6. Response

Method │ Description

respond(status, headers, body) │ Low-level response; sends status + headers + body string in one call

json(data) │ Send JSON: status 200, Content-Type: application/json

text(body) │ Send plain text: status 200, Content-Type: text/plain

html(body) │ Send HTML: status 200, Content-Type: text/html

redirect(url) │ Send HTTP 302 redirect

sendfile(path) │ Serve a file from the filesystem using sendfile(2)

writeHead(status, headers) │ Start a streaming response (headers only)

write(chunk) │ Append a chunk to a streaming response

finish() │ End a streaming response

statusCode (r/w) │ Get or set the response status code

4.2.7. Async Utilities

Method │ Description

sleep(ms) │ Pause the handler for ms milliseconds (non-blocking)

fetch(url [, opts]) │ Make a non-blocking upstream HTTP request; returns Promise<Response>

subrequest(uri) │ Issue an nginx internal subrequest; returns Promise<Response>

4.2.8. Logging

req.log(nginx.INFO, 'Processing request from ' + req.remoteAddr);
// Log levels: nginx.DEBUG, nginx.INFO, nginx.NOTICE, nginx.WARN,
// nginx.ERR, nginx.CRIT, nginx.ALERT, nginx.EMERG

Async Handler Lifecycle

nginx worker event loop
│
├─ accept() → new connection
│
├─ HTTP request parsed
│
├─ location matched → location.handler(req) called
│ │
│ ├─ [sync path] req.json(data)
│ │ └─► response buffered → written to socket → done
│ │
│ └─ [async path] await something
│ │
│ │ Handler suspended. Worker event loop continues:
│ │ • accepts new connections
│ │ • runs other handlers
│ │ • processes timers and upstream responses
│ │
│ ▼ event fires (timer / upstream / Worker message)
│ Promise resolves; handler resumes from the await point
│ │
│ └─► req.json(data) → done
│
└─ (next event)

: Multiple async handlers can be suspended concurrently on the same worker. Each nginx worker runs a single-threaded event loop; async handlers cooperate by yielding at every await point, allowing other requests to be accepted and served in between. Use Workers or SharedWorkers when you need true CPU parallelism or need to share mutable state across workers.

Streaming Responses

loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Send status + headers, then stream the body in chunks.
req.writeHead(200, {'Content-Type': 'text/event-stream',
'Cache-Control': 'no-cache'});
for (let i = 0; i < 5; i++) {
req.write(`data: event ${i}\n\n`);
await req.sleep(200); // 200 ms between events, non-blocking
}
req.finish();
};

Subrequest Fan-Out

// Fire three upstreams in parallel and merge results.
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const [a, b, c] = await Promise.all([
req.subrequest('/internal/prices'),
req.subrequest('/internal/stock'),
req.subrequest('/internal/ratings'),
]);
req.json({
prices: await a.json(),
stock: await b.json(),
ratings: await c.json(),
});
};

Header and Body Filters

Filters are JavaScript functions that run in the nginx filter chain. They are installed on a location object:

// Header filter — modify response headers before they leave nginx
loc.headerFilter = (req, headers) => {
headers['X-Powered-By'] = 'NGINX JS DOM';
delete headers['Server'];
return headers;
};
// Body filter — transform response body chunks
loc.bodyFilter = (req, chunk, isLast) => {
// Replace "foo" with "bar" in every body chunk
return chunk.replace(/foo/g, 'bar');
};

Filters run in priority order (lower number = earlier in chain, default priority 50).

Configuration Object Model (COM)

Overview

The COM is a live JavaScript object tree rooted at the global nginx object. Properties read from the tree return current nginx struct values; writes (on mutable properties) take immediate effect.

nginx
│
├── version — string "1.27.x"
├── cpuCount — number (number of CPU cores)
├── workerMemoryLimit — number (bytes; 0 = unlimited) ← r/w
├── workerRequestTimeout — number (ms; 0 = unlimited) ← r/w
│
├── log(level, msg) — write to nginx error log
├── broadcast(msg) — send msg to all workers' nginx.onbroadcast handler
│
├── suspendAcceptance() — per-worker accept pause (sync)
├── resumeAcceptance() — per-worker accept resume (sync)
├── suspendAllWorkers() — cross-worker quiesce (async, returns Promise)
├── resumeAllWorkers() — cross-worker resume (async, returns Promise)
│
├── cycle
│ ├── connections — number (active connections)
│ ├── freeConnections — number
│ ├── openFilesN — number
│ └── sockets[] — listener socket objects
│
├── events
│ ├── workerConnections — number ← r/w
│ ├── multiAccept — boolean ← r/w
│ └── acceptMutex — boolean ← r/w
│
├── http
│ ├── servers[] — array of NginxServer (see below)
│ ├── upstreams[] — array of NginxUpstream
│ ├── variables{} — nginx HTTP variables
│ ├── serverNamesHashMaxSize ← r/w
│ ├── serverNamesHashBucketSize ← r/w
│ ├── variablesHashMaxSize ← r/w
│ ├── variablesHashBucketSize ← r/w
│ ├── addServer(name) — create a new virtual server at runtime
│ ├── removeServer(name) — remove a virtual server at runtime
│ ├── rebuildVhostDispatch() — recompile the server_name dispatch hash
│ ├── match(req, conditions) — evaluate an `if` condition against a request
│ └── sockets[] — listening socket objects
│
└── stream
├── servers[] — array of stream NginxServer
└── upstreams[] — array of stream NginxUpstream

NginxServer

Each element of nginx.http.servers[] represents a server {} block.

const srv = nginx.http.servers[0];
// Identification
srv.name // primary server_name
srv.names // array of all server_names
srv.listen // array of listen address strings
// Child collections
srv.locations // array of NginxLocation
srv.upstreams // upstreams referenced from this server (if any)
// SSL (if ssl module is compiled in)
srv.ssl.cert // path to certificate ← r/w
srv.ssl.key // path to private key ← r/w
srv.ssl.protocols // "TLSv1.2 TLSv1.3" ← r/w
srv.ssl.ciphers // cipher list ← r/w
srv.ssl.clientCert // path to CA cert for client auth ← r/w
// Dynamic location management
const loc = srv.addLocation('/new-path'); // returns NginxLocation
const loc = srv.addLocation('/api', { template: '/existing-path' }); // copy settings
// from existing loc
// Stream handler (stream {} servers only)
srv.handler = async (session) => { ... };

NginxLocation

const loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(l => l.path === '/api');
// Identification
loc.path // "/api"
loc.exact // true for "= /api" locations
loc.regex // true for "~ /pattern" locations
// Handler
loc.handler = async (req) => { ... };
// Common directives (r/w)
loc.root // document root path
loc.alias // alias path
loc.index // index file list
loc.tryFiles // try_files argument list
loc.sendfile // boolean
loc.gzip // boolean
loc.gzipMinLength // number
// Proxy
loc.proxy.pass // upstream URL ← r/w
loc.proxy.setHeader // {name: value} pairs ← r/w
loc.proxy.readTimeout // ms ← r/w
// Rate limiting, access, auth, headers — all module configs accessible
// (see §14 Reference for full list)
// Per-request write scoping
loc.setWriteMode("global") // write to global config (all future requests)
loc.setWriteMode("local") // write only to a per-request snapshot
loc.setWriteMode("both") // write to both (default)
loc.setReadMode("global") // reads come from global config
loc.setReadMode("local") // reads come from the snapshot (default)

NginxUpstream and Peers

const up = nginx.http.upstreams.find(u => u.name === 'backend');
up.name // "backend"
up.peers // array of NginxRRPeer
const p = up.peers[0];
p.addr // "192.0.2.10:8080"
p.weight // number ← r/w (takes a write lock internally)
p.maxFails // number ← r/w
p.failTimeout // ms ← r/w
p.down // boolean ← r/w (marks peer as permanently down)
p.backup // boolean (read-only)
p.conns // number (active connections, live stat)
p.fails // number (fail counter, live stat)

Iterating the Full Config Tree

// Dump the entire server/location tree to the error log.
for (const srv of nginx.http.servers) {
nginx.log(nginx.INFO, `Server: ${srv.names.join(', ')}`);
for (const loc of srv.locations) {
nginx.log(nginx.INFO, ` ${loc.path} handler=${loc.handler ? 'JS' : 'nginx'}`);
}
}
// Find all locations that use a specific upstream
const byUpstream = nginx.http.servers
.flatMap(s => s.locations)
.filter(l => l.proxy?.pass?.includes('backend'));

Dynamic Reconfiguration

Scope 1 — This Worker Only

The simplest mutations happen directly in a handler with no coordination. The change takes effect immediately for all subsequent requests on this worker. Other workers retain their own CoW copy unchanged.

// Use-case: A/B flag toggle via admin endpoint, applied to this worker.
// Fine for experiments where eventual consistency across workers is acceptable.
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/admin/toggle-gzip')
.handler = (req) => {
// Toggle gzip for the /api location on THIS worker only
const apiLoc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/api');
apiLoc.gzip = !apiLoc.gzip;
req.text(`gzip is now ${apiLoc.gzip}`);
};

Scope 2 — All Workers Atomically

For changes that must be consistent across every worker simultaneously, use suspendAllWorkers / resumeAllWorkers.

Worker A (handler)
│
├─ await suspendAllWorkers()
│ │
│ ├─► sends coordination signal to Workers B, C, …
│ │ Each worker finishes its current request, then:
│ │ • stops calling accept()
│ │ • sends ACK
│ │
│ └─ resolves when ALL workers have ACK'd
│
├─ [mutation window]
│ • Direct COM writes apply to Worker A's copy
│ • SharedWorker broadcast distributes the same data to B, C, …
│ (each worker applies it from its own onmessage handler)
│
├─ await resumeAllWorkers()
│ └─► all workers call ngx_enable_accept_events() and resume
│
└─ respond

adminLoc.handler = async (req) => {
const newPeers = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
// Apply to this worker
const peers = nginx.http.upstreams[0].peers;
newPeers.forEach((p, i) => {
if (peers[i]) peers[i].weight = p.weight;
});
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
req.json({ ok: true });
};

Scope 3 — Add / Remove Servers and Locations

addServer, removeServer, addLocation enable structural mutations — adding or removing routing entries at runtime.

// Tenant onboarding: create a new vhost live, no restart.
nginx.http.servers
.find(s => s.names.includes('admin.internal'))
.locations.find(l => l.path === '/tenant/create')
.handler = async (req) => {
const body = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const domain = body.domain;
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
// Create the new server
const srv = nginx.http.addServer(domain);
srv.listen.push('80');
// Add a root location with a JS handler
const loc = srv.addLocation('/');
loc.handler = (r) => {
r.text(`Welcome to ${domain}!\n`);
};
// Rebuild the server_name dispatch hash so the new Host: domain routes
// correctly to our new server.
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
req.json({ created: domain });
};

// Remove a tenant server (e.g. account deleted).
nginx.http.removeServer('ex-tenant.example.com');
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

: rebuildVhostDispatch() must be called after any change to server names. Without it the Host-based routing hash is stale and requests will be routed to the wrong server.

Scope 4 — Per-Request Config Snapshot

The location.setWriteMode("local") API creates a copy of the location’s config struct scoped to the current request. The global struct is untouched; other concurrent requests see the original values.

loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Write only to a private snapshot for this request.
req.location.setWriteMode('local');
// This change is visible only inside this handler invocation.
req.location.root = '/var/www/' + req.getVar('user_dir');
req.location.gzip = false;
// ... process request ...
// When the request pool is freed, the snapshot is discarded automatically.
};

Hot SSL Certificate Swap

// Admin handler: reload the TLS certificate from disk, zero downtime.
// New connections after this call use the new certificate;
// in-flight TLS sessions are unaffected.
adminLoc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const srv = nginx.http.servers.find(s => s.names.includes(body.domain));
if (!srv) { req.respond(404, {}, 'unknown domain'); return; }
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
srv.ssl.cert = body.certPath;
srv.ssl.key = body.keyPath;
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
req.json({ reloaded: body.domain });
};

Pre-Fork Initialization

7.1.js_preprocess— Config Injection During Parse

js_preprocess evaluates a JS script during ngx_conf_parse, at the exact point where the directive appears in the config file. The script receives a global config object with a single method:

config.write(text) — feeds text back into the nginx config parser exactly as if it had appeared inline at this position.

This happens before init_conf, so nginx.http, nginx.stream, and the full COM are not available. The std and os QuickJS modules are available for file and OS access.

nginx.conf parse reaches js_preprocess /gen.js
│
├─ New JS runtime created (isolated, short-lived)
│
├─ gen.js evaluated
│ • Can read files: std.loadFile('/etc/conf.json')
│ • Can read env: std.getenv('APP_ENV')
│ • Can run commands: os.exec([...])
│ • Can call config.write(text)
│
├─ Runtime freed
│
└─ Injected text re-enters the parser as if it were inline
→ full http{}/server{}/location{} blocks allowed
→ directives go through normal merge/optimize_servers treatment

7.1.1. Example: Server Blocks from a JSON File

// /etc/nginx/js/gen.js
// Generates one server {} block per tenant from a JSON config file.
// Runs once at startup (and again on `nginx -s reload`).
import * as std from 'std';
// Read tenant definitions from a JSON file.
const raw = std.loadFile('/etc/nginx/tenants.json');
const tenants = JSON.parse(raw);
let out = '';
for (const t of tenants) {
out += `
server {
listen 80;
server_name ${t.domain};
root /var/www/${t.id};
location / { }
}
`;
}
config.write(out);

# nginx.conf
js_preprocess /etc/nginx/js/gen.js; # ← generates server{} blocks
events { }
http {
# servers from gen.js appear here as if written manually
}

7.1.2. Example: Conditional SSL Config

// Enable SSL only if the certificate file actually exists.
import * as os from 'os';
const certPath = '/etc/ssl/certs/site.pem';
const keyPath = '/etc/ssl/private/site.key';
// os.stat() returns an object on success, error code on failure.
const [stat, err] = os.stat(certPath);
if (!err) {
config.write(`
ssl_certificate ${certPath};
ssl_certificate_key ${keyPath};
listen 443 ssl;
`);
}

7.1.3. Example: Fetching Config from a Network Service

js_preprocess runs synchronously inside the C parse loop. There is no event loop at this stage, so the standard req.fetch() API is unavailable. The std.urlGet() function (QuickJS std library [https://bellard.org/quickjs/quickjs.html#Standard-library]) works around this by spawning curl as a child process and blocking until the response arrives.

curl must be installed on the system.

// /etc/nginx/js/fetch-config.js
// Download upstream configuration from a config service at startup.
// Uses std.urlGet() which shells out to curl — blocking and synchronous.
import * as std from 'std';
const res = std.urlGet('http://config-service.internal/v1/nginx-upstreams',
{ full: true }); // { status, headers, body }
if (res.status !== 200) {
// Fail loudly — a bad config is worse than a failed start.
throw new Error(`Config service returned ${res.status}`);
}
const cfg = JSON.parse(res.body);
// Generate upstream{} blocks
let out = '';
for (const up of cfg.upstreams) {
out += `upstream ${up.name} {\n`;
for (const peer of up.peers) {
out += ` server ${peer.addr} weight=${peer.weight};\n`;
}
out += `}\n`;
}
config.write(out);

: std.urlGet always spawns a curl subprocess. For reliability in production, prefer writing config data to a file during a pre-start hook and reading it with std.loadFile(), keeping js_preprocess independent of network availability at start time. The network fetch pattern is useful for short-lived tooling or environments where the config service is guaranteed to be reachable.

7.1.4. Multiple js_preprocess Directives

Multiple js_preprocess directives are allowed; each runs in its own isolated runtime in declaration order:

js_preprocess /etc/nginx/js/gen-servers.js; # generates server{} blocks
js_preprocess /etc/nginx/js/gen-upstreams.js; # generates upstream{} blocks
js_preprocess /etc/nginx/js/gen-maps.js; # generates map{} blocks
events { }
http { ... }

7.2.js_init_http— Post-Parse Server Injection

js_init_http fires after the entire http {} block has been parsed but before directive merging takes place. It provides both config.write() and a read-only view of nginx.http.servers[] — the servers parsed before the js_init_http directive.

nginx.conf
│
└── http {
│
├── server { server_name primary.example.com; ... }
│
├── server { server_name secondary.example.com; ... }
│
└── js_init_http /etc/nginx/js/post-parse.js;
│
├─ nginx.http.servers[0] and [1] are readable
├─ config.write(text) injects new servers after these two
└─ injected servers go through normal merge/init_locations treatment

// /etc/nginx/js/post-parse.js
// Add a management server on port 8099 only if no server is already
// listening on that port.
import * as std from 'std';
// Check whether any existing server listens on 8099
const already = nginx.http.servers.some(s =>
s.listen.some(addr => addr.includes(':8099') || addr === '8099')
);
if (!already) {
config.write(`
server {
listen 8099;
server_name management.internal;
location /health { }
location /metrics { }
}
`);
}

: Place js_init_http after the server {} blocks it needs to read. Servers parsed after the directive are not visible to the script.

Workers (JS Web Workers)

JS Workers are background pthreads spawned inside an nginx worker process. They implement the standard Web Worker API [https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Worker] and are the correct tool when a request needs to perform CPU-intensive computation without blocking the event loop.

Each nginx worker process has its own set of Workers; they are not shared between nginx workers.

Basic Worker Pattern

// init.js (js_source)
// Spawn a Worker thread for CPU-intensive prime computation.
// Workers are created once in js_source and reused across all requests.
const computeWorker = new Worker('/etc/nginx/js/prime_worker.js');
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/primes')
.handler = async (req) => {
const n = parseInt(req.queryParams.n) || 100;
// Send work to the Worker thread and await the result.
// While awaiting, the event loop is free to serve other requests.
const result = await new Promise(resolve => {
computeWorker.onmessage = e => resolve(e.data);
computeWorker.postMessage({ n });
});
req.json(result);
};

// /etc/nginx/js/prime_worker.js — runs in a separate pthread
function sieve(n) {
const composite = new Uint8Array(n + 1);
for (let i = 2; i * i <= n; i++) {
if (!composite[i]) {
for (let j = i * i; j <= n; j += i) composite[j] = 1;
}
}
return Array.from({length: n - 1}, (_, i) => i + 2).filter(i => !composite[i]);
}
// Worker message loop
onmessage = (e) => {
const primes = sieve(e.data.n);
postMessage({ count: primes.length, largest: primes[primes.length - 1] });
};

HTTP request → nginx worker event loop
│
├─ handler called; sends postMessage to Worker thread
│ │
│ ▼
│ Worker pthread
│ (independent JS runtime)
│ sieve(n) ← CPU-bound, runs without blocking event loop
│ │
│ ▼
│ postMessage(result)
│ │
│ ▼ onmessage event delivered to event loop
│
└─ Promise resolves; req.json(result) → response sent

Transferring ArrayBuffers (Zero Copy)

Passing an ArrayBuffer by transfer moves ownership; the sender can no longer access it. Use this for large binary payloads:

// Compress a large buffer in a Worker thread, transfer result back.
const compressionWorker = new Worker('/etc/nginx/js/compress_worker.js');
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = await req.readBody();
const input = new TextEncoder().encode(body).buffer; // ArrayBuffer
const compressed = await new Promise(resolve => {
compressionWorker.onmessage = e => resolve(e.data.buf);
// Transfer 'input' — zero copy, Worker takes ownership
compressionWorker.postMessage({ buf: input }, [input]);
});
req.setHeader('Content-Encoding', 'deflate');
req.respond(200, {}, compressed);
};

WorkerstdandosModules

Workers have access to the QuickJS standard library:

// worker.js
import * as std from 'std';
import * as os from 'os';
onmessage = (e) => {
// Blocking file read — safe in a Worker (doesn't block the event loop)
const data = std.loadFile(e.data.path);
postMessage({ content: data, length: data?.length ?? 0 });
};

See QuickJS Standard Library [https://bellard.org/quickjs/quickjs.html#Standard-library] for the full std/os API reference.

SharedWorkers

Concept and Use Cases

A SharedWorker [https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/SharedWorker] is a single long-lived pthread running in the nginx master process, connected to every nginx worker via dedicated UNIX socket channels. Unlike JS Workers (one per nginx worker), there is exactly one SharedWorker instance regardless of the worker_processes count.

This makes SharedWorkers the canonical location for:

•

Session stores — a token → user mapping visible to every worker.

•

Distributed rate limiters — accurate global request-per-second counting.

•

Feature flags — a single flag store; updates propagate to all workers on the next message.

•

Distributed locks — a central lock arbiter that any worker can acquire.

•

Config broadcast — push a config change to all workers simultaneously (see [scope-2-all-workers-atomically]).

Port-Based Pattern (Explicitonconnect)

Use this pattern when a worker needs a dedicated two-way channel with the SharedWorker (i.e. replies must go back to the same worker that sent the request):

// /etc/nginx/js/session_sw.js — SharedWorker script
const store = new Map(); // token → {userId, expires}
// onconnect fires once per nginx worker when the channel is first used.
onconnect = (e) => {
const port = e.ports[0];
port.onmessage = (msg) => {
const { cmd, token, data } = msg.data;
if (cmd === 'get') {
const entry = store.get(token) ?? null;
// Reply only to the worker that asked
port.postMessage({ token, entry });
} else if (cmd === 'set') {
store.set(token, { userId: data.userId,
expires: Date.now() + data.ttl });
port.postMessage({ ok: true });
} else if (cmd === 'del') {
store.delete(token);
port.postMessage({ ok: true });
}
};
};

// init.js (js_source)
const sessionSW = new SharedWorker('/etc/nginx/js/session_sw.js');
// Helper: promise-based call into the SharedWorker.
function swCall(cmd, token, data) {
return new Promise(resolve => {
sessionSW.port.onmessage = e => resolve(e.data);
sessionSW.port.postMessage({ cmd, token, data });
});
}
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/auth')
.handler = async (req) => {
const token = req.cookies['session'];
if (!token) { req.respond(401, {}, 'no session'); return; }
const { entry } = await swCall('get', token, null);
if (!entry || entry.expires < Date.now()) {
req.respond(401, {}, 'invalid or expired session');
return;
}
req.setVar('authenticated_user', entry.userId);
req.respond(200, {}, `Hello ${entry.userId}`);
};

Broadcast Pattern (Globalonmessage+clients)

Use this pattern when the SharedWorker needs to push the same message to all connected workers simultaneously:

// /etc/nginx/js/broadcast_sw.js
// No onconnect — global onmessage handles all workers via the `clients` array.
// `clients` is an array of all currently connected port objects.
onmessage = (msg) => {
if (msg.data.cmd === 'broadcast') {
// Forward the message to every connected worker
clients.forEach(c => c.postMessage(msg.data.payload));
}
};

// init.js: trigger a broadcast from any worker's request handler.
const broadcastSW = new SharedWorker('/etc/nginx/js/broadcast_sw.js');
// Each worker registers a listener on the SW port at init time.
broadcastSW.port.onmessage = (e) => {
// This fires on every worker when a broadcast arrives.
const { key, value } = e.data;
// Apply the change to this worker's local copy of the config.
applyFeatureFlag(key, value);
};
// Admin handler: update a feature flag on all workers at once.
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/admin/feature-flag')
.handler = async (req) => {
const { key, value } = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
// Tell the SharedWorker to broadcast to all workers.
broadcastSW.port.postMessage({
cmd: 'broadcast',
payload: { key, value }
});
req.json({ ok: true });
};

Dynamic SharedWorker Creation

SharedWorkers created in js_source are spawned before fork() and are available to all workers from the start. They can also be created dynamically from a request handler after fork():

// Create a SharedWorker on demand from a handler.
// The SharedWorker is registered globally and subsequent handlers
// calling new SharedWorker('/js/dynamic.js') reuse the same thread.
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const sw = new SharedWorker('/etc/nginx/js/on_demand_sw.js');
const result = await new Promise(resolve => {
sw.port.onmessage = e => resolve(e.data);
sw.port.postMessage({ req: req.uri });
});
req.json(result);
};

SharedWorker Flow Chart

Master process
┌──────────────────────────────────────┐
│ │
│ SharedWorker thread │
│ ┌────────────────────────────────┐ │
│ │ onconnect / onmessage │ │
│ │ shared JS state (Map, arrays) │ │
│ └──────────┬───────────┬──────────┘ │
│ │ │ │
└─────────────┼───────────┼──────────────┘
AF_UNIX SEQPACKET │
┌───────────┘ └────────────┐
│ │
┌────────▼────────────┐ ┌─────────────▼───────────┐
│ Worker 0 │ │ Worker 1 │
│ sw.port.postMessage │ │ sw.port.postMessage │
│ sw.port.onmessage │ │ sw.port.onmessage │
└──────────────────────┘ └─────────────────────────┘

SharedArrayBuffers and Atomics

What They Are

A SharedArrayBuffer [https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/SharedArrayBuffer] is a region of memory accessible — with zero copying — from any thread: nginx workers, JS Workers, and the SharedWorker thread.

Typed array views (Int32Array, Float64Array, BigInt64Array, etc.) over a SAB provide direct read/write access. Atomics [https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Atomics] operations (add, compareExchange, wait, notify) provide the synchronisation primitives needed for safe concurrent access.

Pre-Fork SABs (Visible to All Workers)

A SAB created in js_source is backed by the CoW page mapping inherited by every worker after fork(). All workers share the same physical pages.

// init.js (js_source)
// A global hit counter visible to all workers with zero copy.
const counterBuf = new SharedArrayBuffer(8);
const hits = new BigInt64Array(counterBuf);
// hits[0] is shared by every worker process.
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/count')
.handler = (req) => {
// Atomic increment — safe across all nginx workers simultaneously.
const n = Atomics.add(hits, 0, 1n);
req.text(`Request #${n + 1n}\n`);
};
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/stats')
.handler = (req) => {
req.json({ total_hits: Number(Atomics.load(hits, 0)) });
};

Post-Fork SABs (Worker-Local, Passed via Channels)

A SAB created inside a request handler (post-fork) is backed by a Linux memfd and can be transferred to a JS Worker or SharedWorker via postMessage. The receiving thread `mmap`s the same file descriptor, establishing a shared mapping without copying data.

// Worker thread computes a result into a SAB; main thread reads it.
const processorWorker = new Worker('/etc/nginx/js/processor.js');
loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Allocate shared memory for the result
const resultBuf = new SharedArrayBuffer(1024);
const result = new Uint8Array(resultBuf);
const ready = new SharedArrayBuffer(4);
const flag = new Int32Array(ready);
// Pass both SABs to the Worker; it writes the result and sets flag.
processorWorker.postMessage({
input: JSON.parse(await req.readBody()),
resultBuf, // shared — Worker writes here
ready // shared — Worker sets flag[0]=1 when done
});
// Non-blocking poll using Atomics.wait in the Worker thread
// Meanwhile the event loop remains free.
await new Promise(resolve => {
processorWorker.onmessage = () => resolve();
});
req.respond(200, {}, new TextDecoder().decode(result));
};

Atomics.wait / Atomics.notify

Atomics.wait is a blocking call — it must only be used in Worker or SharedWorker threads, never in the main nginx event loop.

// Mutex implementation using SAB + Atomics.
// Safe to use in Worker and SharedWorker threads.
const mutexBuf = new SharedArrayBuffer(4); // one Int32 = one mutex
const mutex = new Int32Array(mutexBuf);
function lock() {
// Spin until we CAS 0 → 1 (acquire)
while (Atomics.compareExchange(mutex, 0, 0, 1) !== 0) {
// Block this thread until mutex[0] changes — woken by unlock()
Atomics.wait(mutex, 0, 1);
}
}
function unlock() {
Atomics.store(mutex, 0, 0);
// Wake one waiting thread
Atomics.notify(mutex, 0, 1);
}

// In the SharedWorker thread — use Atomics.wait/notify to signal workers.
// SharedWorker receives work, signals the waiting nginx worker via SAB.
onconnect = (e) => {
const port = e.ports[0];
port.onmessage = (msg) => {
const { sab, workItem } = msg.data;
const signal = new Int32Array(sab);
// Do the work ...
const result = processWork(workItem);
// Write result into a different part of the SAB, then notify.
// The nginx worker is blocked in Atomics.waitAsync on this index.
Atomics.store(signal, 0, 1); // mark done
Atomics.notify(signal, 0); // wake the nginx worker's Worker thread
};
};

: Atomics.waitAsync (non-blocking, returns a Promise) is available in the nginx event loop context and is the correct way to wait for a SAB value to change from the main thread.

Accept Control and Cross-Worker Coordination

The Problem

COM mutations applied directly from a handler affect only the worker that executed the handler. Other workers have independent CoW copies and will not see the change. Furthermore, if a mutation is applied while another request on the same worker is halfway through using the old value, the result can be inconsistent.

Accept control solves both problems by temporarily pausing connection acceptance, creating a window during which no new requests can start and the worker is in a known-clean state.

Per-Worker:suspendAcceptance/resumeAcceptance

These are synchronous, instant, and affect only the calling worker.

loc.handler = (req) => {
// Stop accepting new connections on THIS worker.
// OS backlog holds new connections; other workers keep accepting normally.
nginx.suspendAcceptance();
// Apply a batch of mutations atomically from this worker's perspective.
const upstream = nginx.http.upstreams[0];
upstream.peers[0].weight = 10;
upstream.peers[1].weight = 5;
upstream.peers[2].down = true;
// Resume accepting.
nginx.resumeAcceptance();
req.text('upstream updated\n');
};

What happens while suspended:

OS kernel
│
└── TCP SYN backlog accumulates (up to net.core.somaxconn connections)
│
└── When resumeAcceptance() is called, epoll fires again and
the worker drains the backlog in FIFO order.

Other workers are unaffected and continue accepting normally.

Cross-Worker:suspendAllWorkers/resumeAllWorkers

For changes that must be atomic across all workers simultaneously:

Worker A (handler)
│
├─ await nginx.suspendAllWorkers()
│ │
│ ├─ Workers B, C, … receive coordination signal
│ │ Each finishes current request → stops accepting → ACKs
│ └─ resolves when all have ACK'd
│
├─ mutation window (all workers quiesced)
│
├─ await nginx.resumeAllWorkers()
│ └─ all workers re-add listening sockets to epoll
│
└─ req.respond(...)

SharedWorker Broadcast + Accept Control Pattern

The most flexible pattern for cross-worker config updates:

// coord_sw.js — SharedWorker for cross-worker coordination
const ports = []; // one port per connected worker
onconnect = (e) => {
const port = e.ports[0];
ports.push(port);
port.onmessage = (msg) => {
if (msg.data.cmd === 'broadcast_apply') {
// Push the same config update to every worker
ports.forEach(p => p.postMessage({
cmd: 'apply',
config: msg.data.config
}));
}
};
};

// init.js
const coordSW = new SharedWorker('/etc/nginx/js/coord_sw.js');
// Each worker registers a listener to apply inbound config changes.
coordSW.port.onmessage = (e) => {
if (e.data.cmd === 'apply') {
applyConfig(e.data.config);
nginx.resumeAcceptance();
}
};
function applyConfig(cfg) {
// Apply upstream changes to this worker's local copy.
const peers = nginx.http.upstreams[0].peers;
cfg.peers.forEach((p, i) => {
if (peers[i]) {
peers[i].weight = p.weight;
peers[i].down = p.down;
}
});
}
// Admin endpoint: one worker drives the update, broadcasts to all others.
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/admin/config-push')
.handler = async (req) => {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
// Quiesce all workers, apply locally, then broadcast.
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
applyConfig(cfg); // this worker applies locally
// Tell SharedWorker to push to all workers; they will call
// resumeAcceptance() from their onmessage handler.
coordSW.port.postMessage({ cmd: 'broadcast_apply', config: cfg });
// This worker also resumes acceptance.
nginx.resumeAcceptance();
req.json({ pushed: true });
};

Backlog Behaviour

While any or all workers have acceptance suspended, incoming TCP connections queue in the OS SYN/accept backlog:

•

Backlog size is controlled by net.core.somaxconn (typically 128–4096) and the listen directive’s backlog=N parameter.

•

If the backlog fills before resumeAcceptance() is called, the kernel drops new SYN packets. From the client’s perspective this looks like the server is temporarily unavailable.

•

For short mutation windows (sub-millisecond), the probability of backlog overflow is negligible even under high load.

: Do not hold all workers suspended for long operations (database queries, external HTTP calls). Complete all blocking work before calling suspendAllWorkers(), then apply changes synchronously in the mutation window.

Snapshots

Snapshots capture a point-in-time copy of a COM sub-tree. They are useful for rollback, for auditing config state, and for read-heavy operations that must be isolated from concurrent writes.

Basic Snapshot and Rollback

loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Capture the current state of a location before mutating it.
const snap = req.location.snapshot();
try {
// Attempt to apply new configuration.
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
req.location.gzip = cfg.gzip;
req.location.root = cfg.root;
req.location.proxy.pass = cfg.proxyPass;
req.json({ applied: true });
} catch (e) {
// Something went wrong — restore the original state.
snap.restore();
req.respond(500, {}, `Config apply failed: ${e.message}`);
}
};

Sub-Object Snapshots

You can snapshot a specific COM sub-tree rather than the entire config:

// Snapshot just the upstream peer list.
const snap = nginx.http.upstreams[0].snapshot();
// Apply potentially risky changes.
nginx.http.upstreams[0].peers.forEach(p => p.weight = 1);
// If health-check fails, restore peer weights.
const healthy = await runHealthCheck();
if (!healthy) {
snap.restore();
}

Read / Write Mode Interaction with Snapshots

When setWriteMode("local") is active, COM writes go to a per-request snapshot automatically, leaving the global config untouched:

loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Isolate all writes to this request.
req.location.setWriteMode('local');
req.location.setReadMode('local');
// Mutate the per-request copy freely.
req.location.root = '/var/www/' + req.getVar('tenant');
// Other concurrent requests still see the original global root.
req.sendfile('/index.html');
};

Stream (TCP/UDP) Support

The JS DOM API extends to nginx’s stream {} context. Stream handlers receive a NginxStreamSession object instead of NginxRequest.

js_source /etc/nginx/js/stream_init.js;
events { }
stream {
server {
listen 9000;
}
}

// stream_init.js
nginx.stream.servers[0].handler = function(session) {
// Session properties
session.remoteAddress // client IP
session.remotePort // client port
session.localAddress // server-side IP
session.localPort // server-side port (9000)
session.ssl // boolean
session.received // bytes received so far
// Variable access (stream variables)
const proto = session.variable('protocol'); // "TCP" or "UDP"
// Close the session with a status code
session.finalize(); // NGX_STREAM_OK
session.finalize(500); // error
};

Stream COM mirrors the HTTP COM:

// Read stream upstream peers
const peers = nginx.stream.upstreams[0].peers;
peers.forEach(p => nginx.log(nginx.INFO, `${p.addr} w=${p.weight}`));
// Mutate stream upstream peers (same API as HTTP)
peers[0].weight = 20;

External Config Sources and Full Reload

Pattern A — File at Startup (js_preprocess)

Config data is written to a file by an external process (deploy script, Kubernetes operator, config management tool) and read synchronously during nginx startup:

// /etc/nginx/js/from-file.js
import * as std from 'std';
const cfg = JSON.parse(std.loadFile('/etc/nginx/dynamic-config.json') || '{}');
for (const vhost of (cfg.vhosts || [])) {
config.write(`
server {
listen 80;
server_name ${vhost.domain};
root /var/www/${vhost.docroot};
location / { }
}
`);
}

This runs on every nginx -s reload, so the file is the single source of truth.

Pattern B — Network at Startup (js_preprocess+std.urlGet)

See the example in [example-fetching-config-from-a-network-service]. Use this pattern for tooling environments where network availability is guaranteed. In production, pre-download to a file during a health-check or init-container step to avoid coupling nginx startup to network availability.

Pattern C — Live Reload via Handler (Zero Downtime)

For changes that do not require a full restart — upstream weights, SSL certificates, location handlers — apply mutations via the COM from a request handler:

// init.js
function applyConfig(cfg) {
// Update upstream peer weights
if (cfg.upstreams) {
for (const [name, peerCfg] of Object.entries(cfg.upstreams)) {
const up = nginx.http.upstreams.find(u => u.name === name);
if (!up) continue;
for (const [addr, w] of Object.entries(peerCfg)) {
const peer = up.peers.find(p => p.addr === addr);
if (peer) peer.weight = w;
}
}
}
// Hot-swap SSL certificates
if (cfg.ssl) {
for (const [domain, paths] of Object.entries(cfg.ssl)) {
const srv = nginx.http.servers.find(s => s.names.includes(domain));
if (!srv) continue;
srv.ssl.cert = paths.cert;
srv.ssl.key = paths.key;
}
}
}
// Admin endpoint: POST the new config JSON.
nginx.http.servers
.find(s => s.names.includes('admin.internal'))
.locations.find(l => l.path === '/config/apply')
.handler = async (req) => {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
applyConfig(cfg);
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
req.json({ applied: true, ts: Date.now() });
};
// Pull-based reload: a background Worker polls the config service
// periodically and applies changes.
const pollerWorker = new Worker('/etc/nginx/js/config_poller.js');
pollerWorker.onmessage = async (e) => {
if (e.data.type === 'config-update') {
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
applyConfig(e.data.config);
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
}
};

// /etc/nginx/js/config_poller.js — JS Worker thread
import * as std from 'std';
let lastETag = '';
while (true) {
// Poll every 30 seconds
os.sleep(30000);
const res = std.urlGet('http://config-service.internal/v1/nginx-config',
{ full: true });
const etag = (res.headers || {})['etag'] || '';
if (res.status === 200 && etag !== lastETag) {
lastETag = etag;
postMessage({ type: 'config-update', config: JSON.parse(res.body) });
}
}

Decision Guide

Requirement │ js_preprocess │ Pattern C (live) │ Full restart

Generate server/location blocks │ ✓ │ ✗ (can addServer/addLocation, but no merge treatment) │ ✓ (via preprocess)

Network dependency at start time │ Risky (prefer file) │ ✓ │ Risky

Zero downtime │ ✗ (graceful reload) │ ✓ │ ✗

Upstream peer weights │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

SSL certificate rotation │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

New location with full directive inheritance │ ✓ │ Partial (addLocation inherits from template only) │ ✓

Third-Party Module Integration

Overview

Any nginx module can expose its configuration to the COM by implementing a small bridge file that reads the module’s C config structs and projects them as JS properties.

This section walks through adding COM support to a hypothetical ngx_http_mymod module with a main-level config struct.

Step 1 — Identify the Config Structs

/* ngx_http_mymod.h */
typedef struct {
ngx_flag_t enable;
ngx_uint_t max_entries;
ngx_str_t backend_url;
} ngx_http_mymod_main_conf_t;
typedef struct {
ngx_msec_t timeout_ms;
ngx_flag_t cache;
} ngx_http_mymod_loc_conf_t;
extern ngx_module_t ngx_http_mymod_module;

Step 2 — Write the COM Bridge File

Create ngx_js_com_mymod.c next to your module sources:

/* ngx_js_com_mymod.c */
#include <ngx_config.h>
#include <ngx_core.h>
#include <ngx_http.h>
#include "quickjs.h"
#include "ngx_js.h"
#include "ngx_http_mymod.h"
/*
* Getter / setter for main-conf properties.
* 'magic' selects which property (same pattern as NginxRequest).
*/
static JSValue
ngx_js_mymod_main_get(JSContext *ctx, JSValueConst this_val, int magic)
{
ngx_http_mymod_main_conf_t *mcf;
/* Retrieve the main config from the cycle. */
mcf = ngx_http_cycle_get_module_main_conf(ngx_cycle,
ngx_http_mymod_module);
if (mcf == NULL) {
return JS_UNDEFINED;
}
switch (magic) {
case 0: return JS_NewBool(ctx, mcf->enable);
case 1: return JS_NewUint32(ctx, mcf->max_entries);
case 2: return JS_NewStringLen(ctx, (char *) mcf->backend_url.data,
mcf->backend_url.len);
}
return JS_UNDEFINED;
}
static JSValue
ngx_js_mymod_main_set(JSContext *ctx, JSValueConst this_val,
JSValueConst val, int magic)
{
ngx_http_mymod_main_conf_t *mcf;
mcf = ngx_http_cycle_get_module_main_conf(ngx_cycle,
ngx_http_mymod_module);
if (mcf == NULL) {
return JS_EXCEPTION;
}
switch (magic) {
case 0:
mcf->enable = JS_ToBool(ctx, val);
break;
case 1:
JS_ToUint32(ctx, &mcf->max_entries, val);
break;
/* backend_url is an ngx_str_t backed by pool memory — omit setter
or implement with careful pool allocation */
}
return JS_UNDEFINED;
}
/*
* Install nginx.http.mymod into ctx.
* Called from ngx_js_install_nginx_com() during init_conf.
*/
ngx_int_t
ngx_js_com_mymod_install(JSContext *ctx, JSValueConst nginx_obj)
{
JSValue http_obj, mymod_obj;
/* Retrieve the existing nginx.http object. */
http_obj = JS_GetPropertyStr(ctx, nginx_obj, "http");
if (JS_IsUndefined(http_obj)) {
return NGX_ERROR;
}
mymod_obj = JS_NewObject(ctx);
if (JS_IsException(mymod_obj)) {
JS_FreeValue(ctx, http_obj);
return NGX_ERROR;
}
/* Expose enable / maxEntries / backendUrl as JS properties. */
JS_DefinePropertyGetSet(ctx, mymod_obj,
JS_NewAtom(ctx, "enable"),
JS_NewCFunctionMagic(ctx, ngx_js_mymod_main_get, "get_enable", 0,
JS_CFUNC_generic_magic, 0),
JS_NewCFunctionMagic(ctx, ngx_js_mymod_main_set, "set_enable", 1,
JS_CFUNC_generic_magic, 0),
JS_PROP_CONFIGURABLE);
JS_DefinePropertyGetSet(ctx, mymod_obj,
JS_NewAtom(ctx, "maxEntries"),
JS_NewCFunctionMagic(ctx, ngx_js_mymod_main_get, "get_maxEntries", 0,
JS_CFUNC_generic_magic, 1),
JS_NewCFunctionMagic(ctx, ngx_js_mymod_main_set, "set_maxEntries", 1,
JS_CFUNC_generic_magic, 1),
JS_PROP_CONFIGURABLE);
JS_DefinePropertyGetSet(ctx, mymod_obj,
JS_NewAtom(ctx, "backendUrl"),
JS_NewCFunctionMagic(ctx, ngx_js_mymod_main_get, "get_backendUrl", 0,
JS_CFUNC_generic_magic, 2),
JS_UNDEFINED, /* no setter — read-only */
JS_PROP_CONFIGURABLE);
JS_SetPropertyStr(ctx, http_obj, "mymod", mymod_obj);
JS_FreeValue(ctx, http_obj);
return NGX_OK;
}

Step 3 — Register the Bridge in the COM Initialiser

In ngx_js_com.c, locate ngx_js_install_nginx_com and add a call to your bridge function, guarded by whether the module was compiled in:

/* ngx_js_com.c — in ngx_js_install_nginx_com() */
#if defined(NGX_HTTP_MYMOD)
if (ngx_js_com_mymod_install(ctx, nginx_obj) != NGX_OK) {
return NGX_ERROR;
}
#endif

Step 4 — Use from JavaScript

// init.js
nginx.log(nginx.INFO, `mymod enabled: ${nginx.http.mymod.enable}`);
nginx.log(nginx.INFO, `mymod maxEntries: ${nginx.http.mymod.maxEntries}`);
// Toggle mymod from a handler (takes effect immediately for this worker)
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/admin/mymod-toggle')
.handler = (req) => {
nginx.http.mymod.enable = !nginx.http.mymod.enable;
req.text(`mymod is now ${nginx.http.mymod.enable ? 'on' : 'off'}\n`);
};

Location-Level Config

For per-location config, retrieve the conf pointer from the request’s loc_conf array rather than the cycle:

/* In a JS getter called from a request handler context */
static JSValue
ngx_js_mymod_loc_get_timeout(JSContext *ctx, JSValueConst this_val, int magic)
{
ngx_http_request_t *r;
ngx_js_worker_t *w;
ngx_http_mymod_loc_conf_t *lcf;
w = JS_GetContextOpaque(ctx);
r = w->current_request;
if (r == NULL) {
return JS_UNDEFINED;
}
lcf = ngx_http_get_module_loc_conf(r, ngx_http_mymod_module);
return JS_NewUint32(ctx, lcf->timeout_ms);
}

Resource Protection

Worker Memory Limit

nginx.workerMemoryLimit caps the QuickJS heap for all JS allocations in a worker process. The limit applies on top of nginx’s own memory — it measures only memory allocated through the QuickJS allocator.

// Set from js_source — applies to every worker after fork().
nginx.workerMemoryLimit = 128 * 1024 * 1024; // 128 MB per worker
// Read back the configured limit (0 = unlimited).
nginx.log(nginx.INFO, `Memory limit: ${nginx.workerMemoryLimit}`);

When a JS allocation exceeds the limit, QuickJS throws RangeError: out of memory. The worker process remains healthy; the individual request receives a 500 error.

loc.handler = (req) => {
try {
const huge = new ArrayBuffer(512 * 1024 * 1024); // exceeds limit
req.text('allocated\n');
} catch (e) {
// e is RangeError: out of memory
req.respond(503, {}, 'memory limit exceeded, try again\n');
}
};

Worker Request Timeout

nginx.workerRequestTimeout sets the maximum wall-clock time (in milliseconds) a single JS handler invocation may consume. If the handler runs longer than this (including time spent in a tight synchronous loop), QuickJS fires an interrupt that aborts the handler. The worker survives and the request receives HTTP 500.

// Allow each handler at most 5 seconds of wall time.
nginx.workerRequestTimeout = 5000;
// Re-configure at runtime from a handler.
nginx.http.servers[0].locations
.find(l => l.path === '/admin/timeout')
.handler = (req) => {
const ms = parseInt(req.queryParams.ms);
if (ms >= 0) nginx.workerRequestTimeout = ms;
req.text(`timeout is now ${nginx.workerRequestTimeout} ms\n`);
};

Error Isolation

JavaScript exceptions in a handler are caught by the module framework and converted to HTTP 500 responses. The worker process never crashes due to an unhandled JS exception.

loc.handler = (req) => {
// This exception is caught by the framework — worker stays up.
throw new Error('deliberate error');
// Client receives: HTTP/1.1 500 Internal Server Error
};

What JS Cannot Do

The JS runtime runs inside an nginx worker process (or master, for SharedWorkers) with the same OS privileges. The following restrictions apply:

•

No access to nginx’s internal C memory outside the COM API. There is no ctypes, ffi, or equivalent.

•

No subprocess spawning from handlers or SharedWorkers. The os.exec() function from QuickJS os is available only in Workers and js_preprocess scripts, not in nginx event-loop handlers.

•

Blocking the event loop with a synchronous tight loop is interrupted by the request timeout if nginx.workerRequestTimeout is set.

•

Atomics.wait (blocking) must not be called from the event loop; use Atomics.waitAsync (non-blocking, returns a Promise) instead.

Reference

Directives

Directive │ Context │ Arguments │ Description

js_source path │ main │ 1 (path) │ Evaluate path in the master process after config parsing (init_conf). Multiple allowed; evaluated in declaration order. The JS runtime created here is inherited by all workers after fork.

js_preprocess path │ main │ 1 (path) │ Evaluate path immediately when encountered during ngx_conf_parse. Receives global config.write(text). Multiple allowed; each runs in an isolated ephemeral runtime.

js_init_http path │ http │ 1 (path) │ Evaluate path after the http {} block finishes parsing, before merge. Receives config.write(text) and read-only nginx.http.servers[].

17.2.nginxGlobal Object

Property / Method │ Type │ Description

nginx.version │ string │ nginx version string ("1.27.x")

nginx.cpuCount │ number │ Number of CPU cores

nginx.workerMemoryLimit │ number │ QuickJS heap cap in bytes; 0 = unlimited (r/w)

nginx.workerRequestTimeout │ number │ Max handler wall time in ms; 0 = unlimited (r/w)

nginx.log(level, msg) │ — │ Write to nginx error log

nginx.DEBUG/INFO/NOTICE/WARN/ERR/CRIT/ALERT/EMERG │ number │ Log level constants

nginx.broadcast(msg) │ — │ Deliver msg to nginx.onbroadcast on every worker

nginx.onbroadcast │ function │ Set handler for broadcast messages (r/w)

nginx.setTimeout(ms) │ Promise │ Resolve after ms ms (non-blocking)

nginx.cycle │ object │ Cycle-level stats (connections, openFilesN, sockets)

nginx.events │ object │ events{} directives (workerConnections, multiAccept, …)

nginx.http │ object │ HTTP COM tree

nginx.stream │ object │ Stream COM tree

nginx.suspendAcceptance() │ — │ Remove listening sockets from this worker’s epoll

nginx.resumeAcceptance() │ — │ Re-add listening sockets to this worker’s epoll

nginx.suspendAllWorkers() │ Promise │ Quiesce all workers (async)

nginx.resumeAllWorkers() │ Promise │ Resume all workers (async)

17.3.nginx.httpObject

Property / Method │ Type │ Description

servers[] │ array │ Array of NginxServer objects

upstreams[] │ array │ Array of NginxUpstream objects

variables │ object │ nginx HTTP variables (r/w)

serverNamesHashMaxSize │ number │ r/w

serverNamesHashBucketSize │ number │ r/w

variablesHashMaxSize │ number │ r/w

variablesHashBucketSize │ number │ r/w

sockets[] │ array │ Listening socket objects

addServer(name) │ NginxServer │ Create a new virtual server at runtime

removeServer(name) │ boolean │ Remove a virtual server; returns false if not found

rebuildVhostDispatch() │ — │ Recompile the server_name dispatch hash

match(req, conditions) │ boolean │ Evaluate nginx if conditions against a request

NginxRequest Methods and Properties

See [nginxrequest-reference].

Worker / SharedWorker API

JS DOM implements a subset of the standard Web Worker and SharedWorker APIs.

API │ Notes

new Worker(url) │ Spawn a JS Worker thread. url is a path to a JS file.

worker.postMessage(data [, transferList]) │ Send a value to the Worker. Transferable: ArrayBuffer. Shareable: SharedArrayBuffer.

worker.onmessage = fn │ Receive a value from the Worker.

worker.terminate() │ Stop the Worker thread.

new SharedWorker(url) │ Connect to (or create) a SharedWorker. Returns an object with a port property.

sw.port.postMessage(data) │ Send to the SharedWorker.

sw.port.onmessage = fn │ Receive from the SharedWorker.

onconnect = fn (in SW script) │ Fires when a new worker process connects. e.ports[0] is the port.

onmessage = fn (in SW script) │ Global handler; fires for any message from any worker. clients array is available.

clients (in SW script) │ Array of all connected port objects; use for broadcast.

SharedArrayBuffer and Atomics Support Matrix

Operation │ Event loop │ JS Worker │ SharedWorker │ js_preprocess

new SharedArrayBuffer(n) │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Typed array read/write │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Atomics.load/store/add/… │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Atomics.compareExchange │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Atomics.wait (blocking) │ ✗ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Atomics.waitAsync │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✗

Atomics.notify │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓

Transfer via postMessage │ ✓ │ ✓ │ ✓ │ —

: Never call Atomics.wait from the nginx event loop — it blocks the thread, preventing all request processing. Use Atomics.waitAsync in the event loop and Atomics.wait in Workers / SharedWorker threads.

Log Level Constants

Constant │ nginx log level

nginx.DEBUG │ debug

nginx.INFO │ info

nginx.NOTICE │ notice

nginx.WARN │ warn

nginx.ERR │ error

nginx.CRIT │ crit

nginx.ALERT │ alert

nginx.EMERG │ emerg

Appendix — Flow Charts

A: Simple Synchronous Handler

Client → nginx → location matched → handler(req) → req.json() → response

B: Async Handler with Worker Offload

Client → nginx → handler called
│
├── postMessage(input) ────► Worker thread
│ │ CPU work
│ [event loop free] │
│ postMessage(result)
│◄──────────────────────────────┘
└── req.json(result) → response

C: Cross-Worker COM Mutation (suspendAllWorkers)

Client → handler
│
├── await suspendAllWorkers()
│ └─► Workers 1..N finish request, stop accepting, ACK
│
├── [mutation window] mutate COM
│
├── await resumeAllWorkers()
│ └─► Workers 1..N re-enable accept
│
└── req.respond() → response

D: SharedWorker State Coordination

Worker 0 ──postMessage──► SharedWorker (master process)
Worker 1 ──postMessage──► shared JS state (Map, counters, …)
Worker N ──postMessage──► │
route reply ──► correct worker port

E: SAB Lock-Free Counter (Pre-Fork)

js_source: const sab = new SharedArrayBuffer(8); ← master creates
fork() × N workers ← each inherits CoW pages
Worker A: Atomics.add(hits, 0, 1n) ──► kernel mediates CAS on shared page
Worker B: Atomics.add(hits, 0, 1n) ──┘ (no user-space lock needed)

F: Pre-Fork Config Generation

nginx start → conf parse → js_preprocess fires
│
JS reads files / env / network
│
config.write(generated_text)
│
text re-enters parser inline
│
server{}/location{} blocks created with
full merge/init_locations/optimize_servers

G: Live Reload from Config Service

Config service updates Nginx workers running
│ │
▼ │
POST /config/apply all workers quiesced
│ │
▼ suspendAllWorkers()
handler fetches / reads │
new config JSON applyConfig(cfg) per worker
│ │
└──────► COM mutations ────► resumeAllWorkers()
│
all workers resume, serving
requests with new config

H: Complete nginx.* Object Tree

The following tree lists every property and method reachable from the global nginx object, with types and mutability. r/o = read-only; r/w = read-write; fn = function / method.

nginx (global object)
│
├── version string r/o nginx version string, e.g. "1.27.4"
├── workerMemoryLimit number r/w QuickJS heap cap per worker, bytes (0 = unlimited)
├── workerRequestTimeout number r/w Per-handler wall-time cap, ms (0 = unlimited)
│
├── log(level, msg) fn Write to nginx error log
├── broadcast(msg) fn Deliver msg to nginx.onbroadcast on every worker
├── onbroadcast fn r/w Handler called when a broadcast arrives
├── setTimeout(ms) Promise fn Resolve after ms milliseconds (non-blocking)
├── suspendAcceptance() fn Remove listening sockets from this worker's epoll
├── resumeAcceptance() fn Re-add listening sockets to this worker's epoll
├── suspendAllWorkers() Promise fn Quiesce all workers (async)
├── resumeAllWorkers() Promise fn Resume all workers (async)
│
├── cycle (NginxCycle)
│ ├── hostname string r/o system hostname
│ ├── prefix string r/o conf directory (dirname of nginx.conf)
│ ├── confFile string r/o full path to nginx.conf
│ ├── errorLog string r/o path to error log file
│ ├── installPrefix string r/o nginx --prefix
│ ├── pid string r/o path to PID file
│ ├── connectionN number r/o worker_connections value
│ ├── workers number r/w worker_processes count
│ ├── daemon bool r/o daemon on|off
│ ├── master bool r/o master_process on|off
│ ├── timerResolution number r/o timer_resolution in ms (0 = disabled)
│ ├── shutdownTimeout number r/o worker_shutdown_timeout in ms (0 = disabled)
│ ├── priority number r/o worker_priority (nice value)
│ ├── rlimitNofile number r/o worker_rlimit_nofile (-1 if unset)
│ ├── workingDirectory string r/o working_directory ("" if unset)
│ └── sockets[] array r/o NginxSocket — listening sockets snapshot
│
├── events (NginxEvents)
│ ├── connections number r/o worker_connections
│ ├── use string r/o event method ("epoll", "kqueue", …)
│ ├── multiAccept bool r/w multi_accept on|off
│ ├── acceptMutex bool r/w accept_mutex on|off
│ └── acceptMutexDelay number r/w accept_mutex_delay in ms
│
├── http (object)
│ ├── servers[] array r/o NginxServer
│ ├── upstreams[] array r/o NginxUpstream
│ ├── variables object r/o variable name → flags/type map
│ ├── serverNamesHashMaxSize number r/o
│ ├── serverNamesHashBucketSize number r/o
│ ├── variablesHashMaxSize number r/o
│ ├── variablesHashBucketSize number r/o
│ ├── sockets[] array r/o NginxSocket — HTTP listening sockets
│ ├── addServer(name) fn → NginxServer create virtual server at runtime
│ ├── removeServer(name) fn → bool remove virtual server
│ ├── rebuildVhostDispatch() fn recompile server_name dispatch hash (call after addServer/removeServer/setNames)
│ └── match(req, conds) fn → bool evaluate nginx if-conditions
│
└── stream (object)
├── servers[] array r/o NginxStreamServer
└── upstreams[] array r/o NginxStreamUpstream

18.8.1. NginxServer properties

NginxServer (nginx.http.servers[i])
│
├── name string r/o primary server_name
├── names[] array r/o all server_name values
├── listen[] array r/o listen addresses
├── locations[] array r/o NginxLocation
│
├── clientHeaderBufferSize number r/w bytes
├── clientHeaderTimeout number r/w ms
├── connectionPoolSize number r/w bytes
├── requestPoolSize number r/w bytes
├── ignoreInvalidHeaders bool r/w
├── mergeSlashes bool r/w
├── underscoresInHeaders bool r/w
├── serverTokens bool r/w
│
├── ssl NginxSSL (see below)
│
├── setNames(names[]) fn
├── addLocation(path [, {template}]) fn → NginxLocation
├── removeLocation(path) fn → bool
├── findLocation(path) fn → NginxLocation | null
└── clone(name) fn → NginxServer

18.8.2. NginxLocation properties

NginxLocation (server.locations[i] or server.addLocation(…))
│
├── path string r/o location path
├── pattern string r/o compiled regex (regex locations only)
├── matchType string r/o "prefix" | "exact" | "regex" | "named_regex"
├── internal bool r/o
├── jsCreated bool r/o true if created by addLocation()
│
├── handler r/w JS async (req) => {} content handler
├── headerFilters[] array r/o installed header filter entries
├── bodyFilters[] array r/o installed body filter entries
│
├── root string r/w
├── alias string r/w
├── index string r/w
├── defaultType string r/w
├── sendfile bool r/w
├── tcpNopush bool r/w
├── tcpNodelay bool r/w
├── etag bool r/w
├── readAhead number r/w bytes
├── directio number r/w bytes (0 = disabled)
├── directioAlignment number r/w bytes
├── satisfy string r/w "all" | "any"
├── limitExcept string r/w
├── lingering bool r/w
├── lingeringTimeout number r/w ms
├── lingeringTime number r/w ms
├── keepaliveTimeout number r/w ms
├── keepaliveRequests number r/w
├── keepaliveTime number r/w ms
├── keepaliveDisable string r/w "none" | "msie6" | …
├── keepaliveMinTimeout number r/w ms
├── clientMaxBodySize number r/w bytes
├── clientBodyTimeout number r/w ms
├── clientBodyBufferSize number r/w bytes
├── clientBodyInFileOnly bool r/w
├── clientBodyInSingleBuffer bool r/w
├── sendTimeout number r/w ms
├── sendLowat number r/w bytes
├── postponeOutput number r/w bytes
├── sendfileMaxChunk number r/w bytes
├── resetTimedoutConnection bool r/w
├── absoluteRedirect bool r/w
├── serverNameInRedirect bool r/w
├── portInRedirect bool r/w
├── chunkedTransferEncoding bool r/w
├── resolverTimeout number r/w ms
├── authDelay number r/w ms
├── maxRanges number r/w
├── ifModifiedSince string r/w "off" | "exact" | "before"
├── msieRefresh bool r/w
├── msiePadding bool r/w
├── logNotFound bool r/w
├── logSubrequest bool r/w
├── recursiveErrorPages bool r/w
├── typesHashMaxSize number r/o
│
├── ── Module sub-objects (all r/o access; properties within are r/w) ──
├── proxy NginxProxy
├── gzip NginxGzip
├── ssl NginxSSL
├── headers NginxHeaders
├── rewrite NginxRewrite
├── access NginxAccess
├── auth NginxAuth
├── authRequest NginxAuthRequest
├── autoindex NginxAutoindex
├── charset NginxCharset
├── dav NginxDav
├── fastcgi NginxFastCGI
├── gunzip NginxGunzip
├── gzipStatic NginxGzipStatic
├── imageFilter NginxImageFilter
├── limitConn NginxLimitConn
├── limitReq NginxLimitReq
├── log NginxLog
├── memcached NginxMemcached
├── mirror NginxMirror
├── mp4 NginxMp4
├── proxyCache NginxProxyCache
├── randomIndex NginxRandomIndex
├── realip NginxRealIP
├── referer NginxReferer
├── scgi NginxScgi
├── secureLink NginxSecureLink
├── slice NginxSlice
├── ssi NginxSsi
├── subFilter NginxSubFilter
├── tryFiles (object)
├── userid NginxUserid
├── uwsgi NginxUwsgi
├── addition NginxAddition
└── xslt NginxXslt
│
├── setWriteMode("global"|"local"|"both") fn
├── setReadMode("global"|"local") fn
├── setProperty(name, value [, mode]) fn
├── getProperty(name [, mode]) fn
├── addHeaderFilter(name, fn [, priority]) fn
├── addBodyFilter(name, fn [, priority]) fn
├── removeHeaderFilter(name) fn
├── removeBodyFilter(name) fn
└── getHeaderFilter(name) / getBodyFilter(name) fn

18.8.3. NginxUpstream, NginxPeer, NginxRRPeer

NginxUpstream (nginx.http.upstreams[i] or nginx.stream.upstreams[i])
├── name string r/o
├── zone string r/o shared memory zone name ("" if none)
├── peers[] array r/o NginxPeer (config time) or NginxRRPeer (runtime)
├── addPeer(cfg) fn → NginxPeer | NginxRRPeer
└── removePeer(addr) fn → bool
NginxPeer (config-time upstream peer)
├── address string r/o
├── weight number r/w
├── maxFails number r/w
├── failTimeout number r/w seconds
├── maxConns number r/w
├── down bool r/w
└── backup bool r/o
NginxRRPeer (runtime round-robin peer — same as NginxPeer plus:)
├── conns number r/o current active connections
├── fails number r/o current fail counter
└── server string r/o upstream group name
NginxStreamPeer / NginxStreamRRPeer — identical structure to HTTP equivalents

18.8.4. NginxSocket and NginxHttpListener / NginxStreamListener

NginxSocket (nginx.cycle.sockets[i] or nginx.http.sockets[i])
├── address string r/o "host:port"
├── port number r/o
├── fd number r/o OS file descriptor
├── listener r/o NginxHttpListener | NginxStreamListener | null
├── close() fn close and remove socket
└── broadcast() fn send fd to all workers via SCM_RIGHTS
NginxHttpListener (returned by socket listener attach / nginx.http.sockets[i].listener)
├── address string r/o
├── socket NginxSocket r/o
├── serverNames object r/o { name → NginxServer }
├── serverByName(name) fn → NginxServer | null
├── addServer(cfg) fn → NginxServer
└── addVirtualServer(cfg) fn → NginxServer
NginxStreamListener — same shape as NginxHttpListener but returns NginxStreamServer

18.8.5. NginxStreamServer and NginxStreamProxy

NginxStreamServer (nginx.stream.servers[i])
├── serverName string r/o
├── tcpNodelay bool r/w
├── prereadBufferSize number r/w bytes
├── prereadTimeout number r/w ms
├── resolverTimeout number r/w ms
├── proxyProtocolTimeout number r/w ms
├── proxy NginxStreamProxy
├── access NginxStreamAccess
├── ssl NginxStreamSSL
└── handler r/w JS (session) => {} content handler
NginxStreamProxy
├── pass string r/o upstream name
├── connectTimeout number r/w ms
├── timeout number r/w ms (proxy_timeout)
├── nextUpstreamTimeout number r/w ms
├── bufferSize number r/w bytes
├── requests number r/o proxy_requests value
├── responses number r/o proxy_responses value
├── nextUpstreamTries number r/w
├── nextUpstream string r/w
├── proxyProtocol bool r/w
├── halfClose bool r/w
└── socketKeepalive bool r/w

18.8.6. NginxRequest and NginxStreamSession

NginxRequest (handler argument in HTTP content handlers)
│
├── ── Read-only request info ──
├── method string "GET" | "POST" | …
├── uri string path without query string
├── args string raw query string
├── queryParams object parsed {key: value} query parameters
├── scheme string "http" | "https"
├── host string Host header value
├── remoteAddr string client IP
├── remotePort number client TCP port
├── serverAddr string server-side IP
├── serverPort number server-side port
├── httpVersion string "1.0" | "1.1" | "2.0"
├── keepalive bool connection is keep-alive
├── isInternal bool is subrequest
├── startTime number ms since Unix epoch
├── requestLength number total bytes received (headers + body)
├── contentType string Content-Type header value
├── contentLength number Content-Length value
├── connection object nginx connection info
├── headers object request headers (lowercased keys)
├── cookies object parsed cookies {name: value}
├── upstream object upstream peer info (if proxied)
│
├── ── Mutable ──
├── statusCode number r/w response status code
├── variables object r/w nginx variables exotic proxy (r.variables.foo)
├── location NginxLocation r/o matched location (mutable via setWriteMode)
│
├── ── Response ──
├── respond(status, headers, body) fn send complete response
├── json(data) fn 200 + application/json
├── text(body) fn 200 + text/plain
├── html(body) fn 200 + text/html
├── redirect(url) fn 302 redirect
├── writeHead(status, headers) fn begin streaming response
├── write(chunk) fn append streaming chunk
├── finish() fn end streaming response
├── sendfile(path) fn serve file via sendfile(2)
│
├── ── Headers ──
├── setHeader(name, value) fn
├── getHeader(name) fn → string | undefined
└── removeHeader(name) fn
│
├── ── Variables ──
├── variable(name) / getVar(name) fn → string | number | undefined
└── setVariable(name, v) / setVar fn
│
├── ── Body ──
├── body string r/o buffered body (null if not yet read)
└── readBody() Promise fn read full request body → string
│
├── ── Async ──
├── sleep(ms) Promise fn non-blocking delay
├── fetch(url) Promise fn non-blocking upstream HTTP request → Response
└── subrequest(uri) Promise fn nginx internal subrequest → Response
│
└── log(level, msg) fn
NginxStreamSession (handler argument in stream content handlers)
├── remoteAddress string r/o
├── remotePort number r/o
├── localAddress string r/o
├── localPort number r/o
├── received number r/o bytes received so far
├── status number r/o session status code
├── ssl object r/o SSL info (null on plain TCP)
├── finalize([code]) fn close session; default code = NGX_STREAM_OK
└── variable(name) fn → string | undefined

18.8.7. Worker and SharedWorker

Worker (new Worker(url))
├── onmessage fn r/w called when the Worker posts a message
├── postMessage(data [, transferList]) fn send value to the Worker
└── terminate() fn stop the Worker thread
SharedWorker (new SharedWorker(url))
└── port MessagePort
MessagePort (sw.port)
├── onmessage fn r/w called when the SharedWorker posts a message
└── postMessage(data) fn send value to the SharedWorker
── Inside a SharedWorker script ──
onconnect fn r/w fires when a new nginx worker connects; e.data.ports[0] = MessagePort
onmessage fn r/w global handler; receives messages from any worker
clients[] array all connected MessagePort objects (for broadcast)

18.8.8. NginxSSL and NginxStreamSSL

NginxSSL (server.ssl in http context)
├── sessionTimeout number r/w seconds
├── sessionTickets bool r/w
├── preferServerCiphers bool r/w
├── verifyDepth number r/w
├── ciphers string r/o
├── clientCertificate string r/o
├── trustedCertificate string r/o
├── ecdhCurve string r/o
├── dhparam string r/o
├── setCiphers(list) fn change cipher list
├── setProtocols(list) fn e.g. "TLSv1.2 TLSv1.3"
└── setCertificate(cert, key) fn hot-swap certificate and key
NginxStreamSSL (streamServer.ssl in stream context) — same properties plus:
└── handshakeTimeout number r/w ms

I: Full Nginx JS Class Reference

18.9.1. Class Index

Class name │ JS constructor / access path │ Purpose

NginxCycle │ nginx.cycle │ Cycle-level nginx globals

NginxEvents │ nginx.events │ events{} block settings

NginxServer │ nginx.http.servers[i] │ HTTP virtual server

NginxLocation │ server.locations[i], addLocation() │ HTTP location block

NginxUpstream │ nginx.http.upstreams[i] │ HTTP upstream group

NginxPeer │ upstream.peers[i] (config time) │ Upstream server (static)

NginxRRPeer │ upstream.peers[i] (runtime) │ Upstream server (live stats)

NginxRequest │ handler argument req │ HTTP request/response

NginxSocket │ nginx.cycle.sockets[i], http.sockets[i] │ Bound listening socket fd

NginxHttpListener │ socket.listener │ HTTP virtual-host router

NginxStreamServer │ nginx.stream.servers[i] │ Stream (TCP/UDP) server

NginxStreamProxy │ streamServer.proxy │ Stream proxy settings

NginxStreamListener │ socket.listener (stream) │ Stream virtual-host router

NginxStreamSession │ handler argument session │ TCP/UDP session

NginxStreamUpstream │ nginx.stream.upstreams[i] │ Stream upstream group

NginxStreamPeer │ streamUpstream.peers[i] (config) │ Stream upstream server (static)

NginxStreamRRPeer │ streamUpstream.peers[i] (runtime) │ Stream upstream server (live)

Worker │ new Worker(url) │ Background JS thread (per nginx-worker)

SharedWorker │ new SharedWorker(url) │ Shared JS thread (one, in master)

MessagePort │ sharedWorker.port │ Channel endpoint to SharedWorker

NginxSSL │ server.ssl │ HTTP SSL/TLS settings

NginxStreamSSL │ streamServer.ssl │ Stream SSL/TLS settings

NginxProxy │ location.proxy │ proxy_pass and proxy settings

NginxGzip │ location.gzip │ gzip module settings

NginxHeaders │ location.headers │ add_header / expires settings

NginxRewrite │ location.rewrite │ rewrite module settings

NginxAccess │ location.access │ allow/deny access rules

NginxAuth │ location.auth │ auth_basic settings

NginxAuthRequest │ location.authRequest │ auth_request settings

NginxAutoindex │ location.autoindex │ Directory listing settings

NginxCharset │ location.charset │ Charset conversion settings

NginxDav │ location.dav │ WebDAV settings

NginxFastCGI │ location.fastcgi │ FastCGI proxy settings

NginxGunzip │ location.gunzip │ On-the-fly decompression

NginxGzipStatic │ location.gzipStatic │ Pre-compressed file serving

NginxImageFilter │ location.imageFilter │ Image transformation settings

NginxLimitConn │ location.limitConn │ limit_conn settings

NginxLimitReq │ location.limitReq │ limit_req settings

NginxLog │ location.log │ Access log settings

NginxMemcached │ location.memcached │ Memcached proxy settings

NginxMirror │ location.mirror │ Request mirroring settings

NginxMp4 │ location.mp4 │ MP4 pseudo-streaming settings

NginxProxyCache │ location.proxyCache │ Proxy cache settings

NginxRandomIndex │ location.randomIndex │ Random index file settings

NginxRealIP │ location.realip │ Real-IP header settings

NginxReferer │ location.referer │ Referer validation settings

NginxScgi │ location.scgi │ SCGI proxy settings

NginxSecureLink │ location.secureLink │ Secure link settings

NginxSlice │ location.slice │ Response slicing settings

NginxSsi │ location.ssi │ SSI processing settings

NginxSubFilter │ location.subFilter │ Response substitution settings

NginxUserid │ location.userid │ User-ID cookie settings

NginxUwsgi │ location.uwsgi │ uWSGI proxy settings

NginxAddition │ location.addition │ Response addition settings

NginxXslt │ location.xslt │ XSLT transformation settings

NginxStreamAccess │ streamServer.access │ Stream access rules

18.9.2. Module COM Class Properties

Class │ Property │ Mode │ Notes

NginxProxy │ pass │ r/o │ upstream URL or name

NginxProxy │ httpVersion │ r/w │ "1.0" or "1.1"

NginxProxy │ connectTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxProxy │ sendTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxProxy │ readTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxProxy │ buffering │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxy │ requestBuffering │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxy │ interceptErrors │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxy │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxProxy │ nextUpstreamTries │ r/w │ number

NginxProxy │ nextUpstreamTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxGzip │ enable │ r/w │ bool

NginxGzip │ level │ r/w │ 1–9

NginxGzip │ minLength │ r/w │ bytes

NginxGzip │ vary │ r/w │ bool — add Vary: Accept-Encoding

NginxHeaders │ expires │ r/o │ seconds; -1 = epoch; -2 = max; 0 = off

NginxHeaders │ expiresTime │ r/o │ absolute Unix timestamp

NginxHeaders │ headersInherit │ r/w │ bool

NginxHeaders │ trailersInherit │ r/w │ bool

NginxRewrite │ log │ r/w │ bool — log rewrite rule execution

NginxRewrite │ uninitializedVariableWarn │ r/w │ bool

NginxRewrite │ stackSize │ r/w │ number — rewrite stack depth

NginxRewrite │ hasRules │ r/o │ bool — any rules defined

NginxAuth │ realm │ r/w │ string — Basic auth realm

NginxAuth │ userFile │ r/w │ string — path to htpasswd file

NginxAuthRequest │ uri │ r/w │ string — subrequest URI

NginxAutoindex │ enable │ r/w │ bool

NginxAutoindex │ format │ r/w │ "html" | "xml" | "json" | "jsonp"

NginxAutoindex │ localtime │ r/w │ bool

NginxAutoindex │ exactSize │ r/w │ bool

NginxCharset │ charset │ r/o │ string

NginxCharset │ sourceCharset │ r/o │ string

NginxCharset │ overrideCharset │ r/w │ bool

NginxCharset │ setCharset(from, to) │ fn │ add charset conversion mapping

NginxDav │ methods │ r/w │ string[] — allowed HTTP methods

NginxDav │ access │ r/w │ number — octal permissions (e.g. 0o644)

NginxDav │ minDeleteDepth │ r/w │ number

NginxDav │ createFullPutPath │ r/w │ bool

NginxFastCGI │ pass │ r/o │ string

NginxFastCGI │ index │ r/w │ string

NginxFastCGI │ keepConn │ r/w │ bool

NginxFastCGI │ connectTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxFastCGI │ sendTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxFastCGI │ readTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxFastCGI │ buffering │ r/w │ bool

NginxFastCGI │ requestBuffering │ r/w │ bool

NginxFastCGI │ interceptErrors │ r/w │ bool

NginxGunzip │ enable │ r/w │ bool

NginxGzipStatic │ enable │ r/w │ bool — serve pre-compressed .gz files

NginxImageFilter │ action │ r/w │ "test" | "resize" | "crop" | "rotate"

NginxImageFilter │ width │ r/w │ pixels

NginxImageFilter │ height │ r/w │ pixels

NginxImageFilter │ angle │ r/w │ 90 | 180 | 270

NginxImageFilter │ jpegQuality │ r/w │ 1–100

NginxImageFilter │ webpQuality │ r/w │ 1–100

NginxImageFilter │ sharpen │ r/w │ 0–100

NginxImageFilter │ transparency │ r/w │ bool

NginxImageFilter │ interlace │ r/w │ bool

NginxImageFilter │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxLimitReq │ logLevel │ r/w │ log level string

NginxLimitReq │ delayLogLevel │ r/w │ log level string

NginxLimitReq │ statusCode │ r/w │ HTTP status for rejected requests (default 503)

NginxLimitReq │ dryRun │ r/w │ bool — count but do not limit

NginxLimitConn │ logLevel │ r/w │ log level string

NginxLimitConn │ statusCode │ r/w │ HTTP status (default 503)

NginxLimitConn │ dryRun │ r/w │ bool

NginxLog │ off │ r/w │ bool — disable access logging for this location

NginxMemcached │ connectTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxMemcached │ sendTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxMemcached │ readTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxMemcached │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxMemcached │ gzipFlag │ r/w │ number — Memcached flags value for gzip content

NginxMirror │ uris │ r/w │ string[] — mirror target URIs

NginxMirror │ requestBody │ r/w │ bool — mirror request body

NginxMp4 │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxMp4 │ maxBufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxMp4 │ startKeyFrame │ r/w │ bool

NginxRandomIndex │ enable │ r/w │ bool

NginxRealIP │ header │ r/o │ string — header used as client IP source

NginxRealIP │ recursive │ r/w │ bool

NginxReferer │ noReferer │ r/w │ bool — allow requests without Referer

NginxReferer │ blockedReferer │ r/w │ bool — allow requests with blocked Referer

NginxReferer │ serverNames │ r/w │ string[] — allowed referer server names

NginxScgi │ connectTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxScgi │ sendTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxScgi │ readTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxScgi │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxUwsgi │ connectTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxUwsgi │ sendTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxUwsgi │ readTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxUwsgi │ bufferSize │ r/w │ bytes

NginxSecureLink │ secret │ r/w │ string — HMAC secret

NginxSecureLink │ variable │ r/o │ string — variable name holding the link

NginxSecureLink │ md5 │ r/o │ bool — MD5-based (vs HMAC-SHA1)

NginxSlice │ size │ r/w │ bytes — slice size for range-splitting

NginxSsi │ enable │ r/w │ bool

NginxSsi │ silentErrors │ r/w │ bool

NginxSsi │ lastModified │ r/w │ bool

NginxSsi │ valueLen │ r/w │ number — max SSI variable value length

NginxSubFilter │ once │ r/w │ bool — replace only first occurrence

NginxSubFilter │ lastModified │ r/w │ bool

NginxUserid │ enable │ r/w │ bool | "v1" | "v2" | "log"

NginxUserid │ name │ r/w │ string — cookie name

NginxUserid │ domain │ r/w │ string — cookie domain

NginxUserid │ path │ r/w │ string — cookie path

NginxUserid │ p3p │ r/w │ string — P3P header value

NginxUserid │ expires │ r/o │ number — seconds

NginxUserid │ mark │ r/w │ string — version mark character

NginxAddition │ addBeforeBody │ r/w │ string — URI to prepend to response body

NginxAddition │ addAfterBody │ r/w │ string — URI to append to response body

NginxProxyCache │ minUses │ r/w │ number

NginxProxyCache │ lock │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxyCache │ lockTimeout │ r/w │ ms

NginxProxyCache │ lockAge │ r/w │ ms

NginxProxyCache │ revalidate │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxyCache │ convertHead │ r/w │ bool

NginxProxyCache │ backgroundUpdate │ r/w │ bool

NginxXslt │ lastModified │ r/w │ bool

NginxXslt │ sheetsCount │ r/o │ number — number of loaded stylesheets